# Matthew Meehan

## Professional Summary

Particle astrophysicist with big data expertise excited to apply analysis and machine learning skills to human-facing problems. Analytical problem solver with five years of experience performing data-driven research with Python, building statistical models, and communicating complex, technical results to diverse audiences in conference and outreach settings.

# SKILLS

- General: Data science, statistics, data visualization, machine learning, deep learning, computer vision
- Technical: Python, NumPy, SciPy, scikit-learn, Keras, matplotlib, HTCondor, linux, Git, LATEX
- Other: Scientific communication, technical problem solving, teaching, mentoring, physics

#### Work Experience

# Wisconsin IceCube Particle Astrophysics Center

Madison, WI

Research Assistant

May 2014 - Present

- Performed big data analysis of astrophysical data from NASA's Fermi Large Area Telescope on a distributed, high-throughput computing cluster (100 GB 100 TB scale pipelines)
- Developed and deployed a covolutional neural network to identify images of particles detected by a network of smartphones with 95% accuracy
- Utilized Monto-Carlo simulations to quantify algorithmic biases and systematic uncertainties for cosmic-ray measurements at the 0.1% level
- Created unbiased, data-driven algorithms to estimate physical parameters of cosmic-ray arrival direction distribution
- Developed random forest regression model to estimate angular uncertainty of cosmic rays detected by the Fermi telescope
- Worked in an international collaboration of 400+ scientists, coordinate working group, co-chair weekly international conference calls
- Regularly presented work at national and international conferences
- Mentored undergraduate researchers and high school students on data analysis projects

### Department of Physics, University of Wisconsin-Madison

Madison, WI

Teaching Assistant

August 2013 - May 2014

- Designed discussion curriculum and taught calculus-based electricity and magnetism course to 50 engineering students each semester
- Received Honored Instructor award for teaching excellence (nominated by students)

#### EDUCATION

University of Wisconsin-Madison	Madison, WI
Ph.D., Physics (graduating Dec 2018)	2013 - 2018
M.S., Physics	2013 - 2016
Kutztown University of Pennsylvania	Kutztown, PA
B.S., Physics, Minor, Mathematics	2010 - 2013

## SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- M. Winter, J. Bourbeau, M. Meehan, J. Vandenbroucke, et al., Particle Identification In Camera Image Sensors Using Computer Vision. Astroparticle Physics, 104 (2018), 42-53. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.astropartphys.2018.08.009.
- M. Meehan, J. Vandenbroucke, for the Fermi-LAT Collaboration, A Search for Cosmic-ray Proton Anisotropy with the Fermi Large Area Telescope. Proceedings of Science. (ICRC2017) 170. https://doi.org/10.22323/1.301.0170.